{"tossups": [{"question": "Colonists in this state protested a British law in the Pine Tree Riot. Following the Antinomian Controversy, Puritan John Wheelwright founded this state's town of Exeter. Queen Anne's War was ended by a treaty named for this state's city of Portsmouth. Daniel Webster defended his alma mater located in this state in the case <em>Dartmouth College v.</em> <em>Woodward</em>. Franklin Pierce was born in, for ten points, what New England \"Granite State\" governed from Concord?", "answer": "<b><u>New Hampshire</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man became a Member of Parliament for Birmingham Ladywood, his first elected position, at the age of 49. This man recommended the abdication of Edward VIII, while serving as Chancellor of the Exchequer to Stanley Baldwin. On September 30, 1938, this man conceded the Sudetenland to Germany, and declared war on the latter after its invasion of Poland in 1939. For ten points, name this man, who served as Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1937 to 1940.", "answer": "Neville <b><u>Chamberlain</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The earliest known instance of this designation was an 836 AD link between Paderborn and Le Mans. Instances of this special bond increased significantly after World War Two, when Coventry was grouped with both Stalingrad and Dresden. Boston has eleven of these international relationships, while New York has more than one hundred. For ten points, name this type of connection intended to foster understanding, friendship, and tourism between cities in different countries.", "answer": "<b><u>Sister citie</u></b>s or <b><u>Twin town</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this action, the 78th Fraser Highlanders took heavy casualties from a French battery on the St. Charles River. This battle was preceded by an amphibious landing by the British at L'Anse-au-Foulon [[LAHNCE-oh-foo-LAWHN]]. The commanding generals, Louis Montcalm and James Wolfe, were both mortally wounded during this battle. For ten points, name this decisive 1759 battle, fought on the Plains of Abraham, where British troops captured a French-speaking city in Canada.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Quebec</u></b> (or Battle of the <b><u>Plains of Abraham</u></b> before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s only remaining Native American reservation was established by Anglican missionary William Duncan and the Tsimshian [[shim-SHEE-uhn]] people. This state\u2019s senator Ted Stevens was criticized for pushing the \u201cBridge to Nowhere\u201d project. During World War Two, Japanese invaders transported natives from this state's islands of Attu and Kiska to Hokkaido. For ten points, name this state, home to various Aleut and Inuit tribes, as well as the cities of Juneau and Anchorage.", "answer": "<b><u>Alaska</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "People serving England\u2019s Richard II wrote a work of this type called <em>The Forme of</em> <em>Cury</em> [[KYEW-ry]]. A subversive work of this sort, authored by William Powell, provides instructions for making drugs and weapons. One of these guides, written in 1845 by Eliza Acton, contained the first known appearance of the word \u201cspaghetti\u201d in English print. Fannie Farmer wrote instructions for making aspic and popovers in, for ten points, works of what literary genre intended for homemakers and chefs?", "answer": "<b><u>Cookbook</u></b> (accept similar answers indicating <b><u>book</u></b>s about preparing food)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This leader, along with Maria Theresa and Prince Henry of Prussia, defeated and partitioned the Polish-Lithuanian Empire. This ruler also absorbed many lands of the Ottoman Empire and colonized Russian Alaska. This ruler\u2019s personal collection of books and art was the foundation of what became the Hermitage Museum. This ruler came to power following a coup that unseated her husband and second cousin, Peter the Third. For ten points, name this Empress of All Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Catherine the Great</u></b> or <b><u>Catherine II</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first of these machines in the United States was completed by Ernest O. Lawrence in 1930 and was used at the University of California-Berkeley. In a 1954 address to the American Physical Society, Enrico Fermi proposed building one of these machines in stable orbit around the circumference of the Earth. The current largest of these machines is located 175 meters below ground on the border of France and Switzerland, and is seventeen miles in circumference. For ten points, name these machines used in particle physics experiments to propel charged particles.", "answer": "<b><u>Particle accelerator</u></b>s (or <b><u>Particle collider</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Cyclotron</u></b> prior to \"1954\")", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This peninsula is connected to the mainland by the Bourne and Sagamore bridges, spanning this peninsula\u2019s namesake canal. In 1902, Guglielmo Marconi made the first transatlantic wireless transmission from Wellfleet, on this peninsula. Located in Barnstable County, this peninsula hosts a family compound in Hyannis Port, which John F. Kennedy used as his so-called \u201cSummer White House.\u201d For ten points, name this Massachusetts peninsula adjacent to Martha\u2019s Vineyard and Nantucket.", "answer": "<b><u>Cape Cod</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A museum dedicated to this man is located in Hamden, Connecticut, on the grounds of a gun factory that he built there. Prior to becoming an inventor, this man had planned to attend law school after graduating from Yale, where a non-traditional student admissions program is named for him. After this man popularized interchangeable parts, the federal government contracted him to help manufacture arms. For ten points, name this American inventor of the cotton gin.", "answer": "Eli <b><u>Whitney</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Grace Kelly invited this man to Monaco in 1958 to arrange a benefit concert with Frank Sinatra at the Monaco Sporting Club. In 1968, Bob Russell and this man became the first African-Americans to be nominated for an Academy Award for Best Original Song for \u201cThe Eyes of Love\u201d from the film <em>Banning</em>. In 1984, this man won the Grammy for Album Of The Year for producing Michael Jackson\u2019s <em>Thriller</em>. For ten points, name this legendary music producer, who holds the record for all-time Grammy nominations.", "answer": "Quincy <b><u>Jones</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man lost his son during the joint Allied offensive at the Battle of the Loos, inspiring his poem \"My Boy Jack.\" In a novel by this man, orphan Kimball O'Hara becomes an intelligence officer at the height of the \u201cGreat Game\u201d in Central and South Asia between the British and Russian Empire. Inspired by the failed Jameson raid and subsequent outbreak of the Second Boer War, this author wrote the poem \u201cIf\u2014\u201d found in his collection <em>Rewards and Fairies</em>. For ten points, name this British author who set many of his works in British India like \u201cThe Man Who Would Be King\u201d and <em>The Jungle Book</em>.", "answer": "Rudyard <b><u>Kipling</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Guy Hopkins attempted to implicate this man as a member of the Knights of the Golden Circle, and James Dobbin's speech for this man aided his nomination. Shortly after his election, this man's son, Benjamin, was killed in a train crash, causing the First Lady to avoid public events for two years. This man purchased part of Mexico with the Gadsden Purchase and his diplomats authored the Ostend Manifesto. For ten points, name this 14th US president.", "answer": "Franklin <b><u>Pierce</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This group fought Valdemar IV of Denmark after he sacked Visby on the island of Gotland. Crews in this group were called <em>Schiffskinder</em>, and the Bay Fleet travelled from the English Channel to trade with this group. The Victual Brothers were initially supported by this group. This league's trading ports were called <em>Kontors</em>, and its member cities included Hamburg and L\u00fcbeck. For ten points, name this league of merchant states along Northern Europe and the Baltic sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Hanseatic</u></b> League (accept <b><u>Hansa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The first observance of this holiday in the US occurred at Columbia State Park in 1863. This holiday originated from a war of which historian John Leddy Phelan claims Napoleon III wanted to create \"Latin America.\u201d This holiday commemorates the victory of Ignacio Zaragoza against Charles de Lorencez at the Battle of Puebla, which was followed by the installation of Maximilian I and the Second Mexican Empire. For ten points, name this celebration, often associated with Mexican-Americans.", "answer": "<b><u>Cinco de Mayo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Fifth of May</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Nonny de la Pe\u00f1a implicated this agency in a death in a virtual reality journalism piece. This agency gives out the Newton-Azrak Award for Heroism and was itself created by the Johnson-Reed Act of 1924. This agency launched Operation Gatekeeper and created the BORSTAR search and rescue unit. This agency uses line watch and roving patrol strategies and operates 71 traffic checkpoints on many major US highways. For ten points, name this arm of the CBP, the police force tasked with preventing unauthorized entry into the US.", "answer": "U(nited) S(tates) <b><u>Border Patrol</u></b> (prompt on \"USBP\"; do not accept or prompt on \"ICE\" or \"Immigrations and Customs Enforcement\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Mary Dietz argues that this work was not meant to be satirical. This work extols Agathocles of Syracuse and Oliveretto Euffreducci. In this work, the execution of Remirro de Orco by Cesare Borgia is given as an example of conquest by fortune. This work is often compared to its author's less known work, <em>Life of Castruccio Castracani</em>. This work was addressed to the Duke of Urbino, Lorenzo de' Medici, and uses the metaphors of the lion and fox. For ten points, name this political treatise by Machiavelli.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Prince</u></b></em> (accept <em>Il</em> <em><b><u>Principe</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "A philosopher from this country created the Black Repartition and the \"Emancipation of Labor Group,\u201d and authored <em>The Development of the Monist view of History</em>. Another author from this country, an anarchist who spent 41 years in exile in Switzerland, worked with Jean Grave on the <em>Manifesto of the Sixteen</em> and authored <em>The Conquest of Bread</em>. Georgi Plekhanov and Peter Kropotkin were philosophers from, for ten points, what country once ruled by the Tsars?", "answer": "Empire of <b><u>Russia</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \"Soviet Union\" or \"USSR\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "American variety of the <em>vaquero</em>, a ubiquitous Western animal herder.", "answer": "<b><u>Cowboy</u> </b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "1862 Act that allowed for settlers to claim farms, conflicting with ranchers.", "answer": "<b><u>Homestead</u></b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Large Great Plains animals that were simultaneously slaughtered en masse as cattle population grew.", "answer": "American <b><u>bison</u></b> (accept American <b><u>buffalo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Metal invention of Joseph Glidden, a means of fencing in cattle.", "answer": "<b><u>Barb</u></b>ed wire (accept <b><u>Bob</u></b>bed wire)   Term for a skilled Argentine horseman, central to South American ranching culture. (5)  ANSWER: <b><u>Gaucho</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Cattle trail on which Margaret Borland drove 2500 cattle from Texas to Wichita.", "answer": "<b><u>Chisholm</u></b> Trail", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "British captain who charted the coast of British Columbia and brought cattle to Hawaii.", "answer": "George <b><u>Vancouver</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Eastern island location of Deep Hollow Ranch, reputed to be the first ranch in the US.", "answer": "<b><u>Long Island</u></b>, New York", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "System under which serfdom flourished involving landowners exchanging use of their land for peasant labor.", "answer": "<b><u>Feudal</u></b>ism", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Last European empire to outlaw serfdom, done so by Tsar Alexander II.", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Thinker who stated both serfdom and free labor are equally primitive in <em>Das Kapital</em>.", "answer": "Karl <b><u>Marx</u> </b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "14th century \u201cRevolt\u201d led by Wat Tyler which effectively ended serfdom in England.", "answer": "<b><u>Peasants'</u></b> Revolt (accept the <b><u>Great Rising</u></b>, prompt on \"Wat Tyler's Rebellion) People of the steppe who united with serfs in Pugachev's Rebellion which captured (5)  the city of Kazan.  ANSWER: <b><u>Cossack</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Medieval tenant farmers with great autonomy who were legally bound to a manor.", "answer": "<b><u>Villein</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cotter</u></b>, accept <b><u>Crofter</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Term for serfs or slaves in Viking societies, often used as a punishment for a failure to repay debts.", "answer": "<b><u>Thrall</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Economist who claimed collectivist policies led to destitution in <em>The Road to</em> <em>Serfdom</em>.", "answer": "F(riedrich) A(ugust) von <b><u>Hayek</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "Religion whose missionaries were labelled as \u201cdevils\u201d by the Boxers.", "answer": "<b><u>Christian</u></b>ity (anti-prompt on \"Catholicism\" or other <b><u>Christian</u></b> denominations)) (2) Manchurian dynasty during which the rebellion occurred.  ANSWER: Great <b><u>Qing</u></b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Capital whose occupation by the Gaselee Expedition nominally ended the rebellion.", "answer": "<b><u>Beijing</u></b> (accept <b><u>Peking</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Asian nation that defeated China in an 1895 war, setting the stage for the rebellion.", "answer": "Empire of <b><u>Japan</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "General name for the one-sided \u201cTreaties\u201d China signed with the West, including the Boxer Protocol.", "answer": "<b><u>Unequal</u></b> Treaties", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Future US President trapped in China during the rebellion while working as a mining engineer.", "answer": "Herbert <b><u>Hoover</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "\u201cAlliance\u201d of countries which subdued the rebellion through military intervention.", "answer": "<b><u>Eight-Nation</u></b> Alliance", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Province of China in which the rebellion began and whose city of Qingdao [[CHING-DOW]] was leased to Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Shandong</u></b> (or <b><u>Shantung</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After the Farmington disaster of 1968 involving this resource, a Federal</u></b> <b><u>Health and Safety Act was passed to protect people working in the business</u></b> <b><u>associated with this resource. A 1920 shootout between laborers in this industry and</u></b> <b><u>members of the Baldwin-Felts Detective Agency took place in (+)</u> Matewan, West Virginia. Workers who help to extract this resource can suffer from excessive powder inhalation, or (*) </b>\u201cblack lung.\u201d For ten points, name this sedimentary fossil fuel, extracted from underground \u201cseams.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Coal</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A politician from this nation was elected \u201cRegenerating President\u201d after</u></b> <b><u>calling for peace in the \u201cCry of Mont\u00e1n.\u201d An admiral from this country was nicknamed</u></b> <b><u>the \u201cGentleman of the Seas\u201d after rescuing the crew of the</u> </b><em><b><u>Esmeralda</u></b></em><b><u> when he</u></b> <b><u>defeated them at the Battle of (+)</u> Iquique [[ih-KWEE-kweh]]. This nation\u2019s monopoly on saltpeter sparked a war with neighboring (*) </b>Chile. For ten points, name this ally of Bolivia during the War of the Pacific, which in 2020 elected President Francisco Sagasti to govern from the House of Pizarro in Lima.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Peru</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This movement was aided by Lucas Cranach, who helped create artistic</u></b> <b><u>propaganda to spread its beliefs. This movement\u2019s focus on vernacular writing</u></b> <b><u>helped achieve a higher level of literacy in Europe. Metaphorically, this movement</u></b> <b><u>hatched the egg that (+)</u> Erasmus laid. In 1531, the Peace of Augsburg helped achieve the goals of this movement which began after a German (*) </b>monk wrote against the practice of indulgences. For ten points, name this movement against the Catholic Church, started in 1517 by Martin Luther.", "answer": "Protestant <b><u>Reformation</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \u201ccounter-reformation\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>\u00c9tienne G\u00e9rard defended this country in a failed attempt to reconquer it</u></b> <b><u>known as the Ten Days\u2019 Campaign. A revolution in this country began during a</u></b> <b><u>performance of the opera</u> </b><em><b><u>The Mute Girl of Portici</u></b></em><b><u> [[por-TEE-chee]], presented during</u></b> <b><u>a celebration of William I, Prince of (+)</u> Orange-Nassau. This country\u2019s independence was recognized at the London Conference, but it took nine years for the (*) </b>Netherlands to accept it. For ten points, name this country whose 1830 revolution led to the establishment of a government in Brussels.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Belgium</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of the colors of this flag represents both the hue of the rhododendron</u></b> <b><u>flower and bravery, while the color of its border represents peace and harmony. An</u></b> <b><u>earlier version of this flag featured two human faces, but those faces were removed</u></b> <b><u>from its (+)</u> sun and moon in 1962. When constructed according to the process mandated in its country\u2019s 2015 Constitution, this flag\u2019s aspect ratio is an (*) </b>irrational number. For ten points, name this emblem of an Asian nation, the world\u2019s only non-quadrilateral national standard.", "answer": "<b><u>Flag</u></b> of <b><u>Nepal</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Members of this ethnic group blew up the car of a prime minister nicknamed</u></b> <b><u>his country's \"first astronaut\" in Operation Ogre. Whalers of this ethnic group who</u></b> <b><u>spoke an Algonquian-based pidgin were massacred in 1615 in Iceland. Luis Carrero</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Blanco was killed by a terrorist group of this ethnic group called the ETA, which was falsely blamed for the 2004 Madrid train bombings. Francisco Franco attempted to suppress this ethnic group by carrying out the (*) </b>bombing of Guernica. For ten points, name this Spanish ethnic group, who speak a language isolate called Euskara.", "answer": "<b><u>Basque</u></b>s (or <b><u>Euskaldunak</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This composer depicted an encounter between Death and Don Juan in his</u></b> <b><u>second symphony, which he wrote in Italy. This man did not compose any music for</u></b> <b><u>the last thirty years of his life following the release of his single-movement seventh</u></b> <b><u>symphony and the tone poem (*)</u> </b><em><b>Tapiola</b></em><b>. This composer\u2019s best known tone poem premiered in 1899 as a protest against Russian censorship. This man's piece, </b><em><b>The </b><b>Swan of Tuonela</b></em><b>, was inspired by the (*) </b><em>Kalevala</em>. For ten points, name this namesake of a music notation program who wrote <em>Finlandia</em>.", "answer": "Jean <b><u>Sibelius</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This battle's namesake campaign ended with the Battle of Forts Clinton and</u></b> <b><u>Montgomery. Redoubts at this battle were led by Lord Balcarres and Heinrich von</u></b> <b><u>Breymann. Timothy Murphy likely shot and killed Simon Fraser at this battle. The</u></b> <b><u>surrendered troops formed the (+)</u> Convention Army at this battle, which led to a Franco-American alliance. This battle included fights at Bemis (*) </b>Heights and Freeman's Farm. For ten points, name this 1777 battle at which Horatio Gates defeated John Burgoyne in upstate New York.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Saratoga</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Robert Ritter and Eva Justin were assigned to investigate these people who</u></b> <b><u>were targeted at Szczurowa [[shoo-ROFF-ah]]. The Czechs held these people at Lety</u></b> <b><u>camp as related in the book</u> </b><em><b><u>Black Silence</u></b></em><b><u> and were also held by the Germans at the</u></b> <b><u>Berlin- (+)</u> Marzahn camp. In concentration camps, these people were made to wear inverted brown triangles or the letter \"Z.\u201d Prejudice toward these people is called (*) </b>\u201cantiziganism.\u201d For ten points, name these people who often lived nomadic lives out of wagons throughout Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Roma</u></b>ni (accept <b><u>Gypsy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}